# Aravinth Sadagopan

Email: azs381@psu.edu, saravinth841@gmail.com

Developing data-driven/theoretical reduced-order models (ROMs) for complex fluid flows. Collaborated with experimental groups on multi-physics problems focusing on computational model validation and flow field analysis. Experience in turbomachinery aerodynamics, high-speed flows, and computational aeroelasticity.

#### EDUCATION

#### The Pennsylvania State University

University Park, PA

Mobile: (814)862-8679

LinkedIn Webpage

Doctor of Philosophy - Aerospace Engineering; GPA: 4/4

July 2019 - Present

Thesis: Fluid-Thermal-Structural interaction of a Cone-Slice-Ramp in High-Speed Flows

The Pennsylvania State University

University Park, PA

Master of Science - Aerospace Engineering; GPA: 3.93/4

Aug 2016 - May 2019

Thesis: A Design Strategy for a 6:1 Supersonic Mixed-Flow Compressor Stage and its Viscous Flow-based Performance Assessment

Amrita Vishwa Vidyapeetham

Coimbatore, India

Bachelor of Technology - Aerospace Engineering; GPA: 8.89/10

Aug 2012- May 2016

### Honors and Awards

Distinguished Master's Thesis Award (2019)

ASME International Gas Turbine Institute (IGTI) Student Scholarship (2017)

#### Research experience

# The Pennsylvania State University

University Park, PA

Aerospace multi-physics and unconventional systems lab, PI: Dr. Daning Huang

 $Graduate\ Student$ 

# Computational Aeroacoustic Analysis of Jet Nozzle Flows

Jan 2024 - present

• Collaborating with Dr. Philip Morris (PSU) on the FAA ASCENT project to develop an efficient computational coarse LES-based framework (low-fidelity) to predict noise during landing and take-off of supersonic jets.

#### Data-Driven Input-Output Analysis of Fluid Flows with Quasi-Periodic Behavior

- Establishing the causal mechanism of a fluid system from data leveraging information about the governing equation. Building effective reduced-order models (ROM) combining dimension reduction and operator learning.
- Employed bi-spectral methods to characterize energy transfer on high-speed cavity flows (a quasi-periodic system).

# ROM for Fluid-Thermal-Structural Interaction of Cone-Slice-Ramp (CSR)

Dec 2024 - Present

- Proposed a ROM-based FTSI framework to evaluate CSR-type geometries for a range of ramp angles at the low-Reynolds number inflow condition.
- Developing a fluid ROM based on composite analytical method and deep networks. Validated the thermo-structural module based on shell-finite element and modal solver.

#### Characterization of compressible shear layers of Cone-Slice-Ramp

Jan 2022- Jan2024

- Collaborated with Sandia National Laboratories (SNL) to investigate the compressible shear layer of cone-sliceramp using LES. Flow features include shockwave/boundary layer interaction, low-frequency oscillation, shear layer flapping, and streamwise streaks and vortices. HPC resource: PSU ICDS Roar.
- Developed a local and biglobal stability analysis framework to extract modal and non-modal amplification mechanisms of compressible fluid flows using finite difference and spectral methods (Direct and Iterative solvers). Parallel version: SLEPc.

# Numerical Investigation of FTSI on a Cone-Slice-Ramp in Hypersonic Flows

Jan 2020- May 2022

- Lead the joint experimental/computational collaborative effort with SNL and USAFA to investigate the FTSI behavior of CSR that emulates the control surface of a flight vehicle.
- Validated the high-fidelity FTSI computational framework comprising implicit LES, and FEM/Rayleigh-Ritz models. Discovered the interaction mechanism of this multi-physics problem. HPC resource: PSU ICDS Roar.

# The Pennsylvania State University

University Park, PA

Turbomachinery Aero-Heat Transfer Lab, PI: Dr. Cengiz Camci

 $Graduate\ Student$ 

# Numerical Modeling of an HP Turbine Stage for Tip Leakage Flow Mitigation

Aug 2018 - May 2019

- Validated the computational model of a high-pressure (HP) Turbine stage at PSU-AFTRF experimental facility with RANS-based CFD using STAR-CCM+. Characterized the aerothermal losses due to tip leakage, and secondary flows in the blade passage to perform tip-design studies.
- Compared the effectiveness of various turbomachinery simulation techniques: mixing plane, sliding mesh, and harmonic balance method.

Design analysis of a 6:1 supersonic mixed-flow compressor (MFC): Master's Thesis Jan 2017 - July 2018

- Proposed a single-stage high-pressure ratio compressor using first-order principles to address the surging demand in the small aircraft engine segment (1-10 kg/s).
- Optimized the design, validated and examined the flow physics with RANS-baed CFD using STAR-CCM+. A design point pressure ratio of 5.83 with 75.5% efficiency at 3.5Kg/s was achieved within 0.4m frontal diameter (higher performance than existing MFCs in the open literature).

#### PEER REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

- 1. **Sadagopan, A.**, Huang, D., "Reduced-order modeling for Fluid-Thermal-Structural interaction of Cone-Slice-Ramp in high-speed flows", *in progress*.
- 2. **Sadagopan, A.**, Huang, D., Pandey, A., Casper, K., DeChant, L., "Compressible shear layer dynamics of a coneslice-ramp in high-speed flows", in progress.
- 3. Sadagopan, A., Huang, D., Jirasek, A., Seidel, J., Pandey, A., Casper, K., "Hypersonic Fluid-Thermal-Structural Interaction of Cone-Slice-Ramp: Computations with Experimental Validation," AIAA Journal, 2023. DOI:10.2514/1.J062326
- 4. Huang, D., **Sadagopan, A.**, Duzel, U., Hanquist, K., "Study of Fluid-Thermal-Structural Interaction in High-Temperature High-Speed Flow using Multi-Fidelity Multi-Variate Surrogates", Journal of Fluids and Structures, 2022. DOI:10.1016/j.jfluidstructs.2022.103682
- 5. **Sadagopan, A.**, Camci, C., "A design strategy for a 6:1 supersonic mixed flow compressor", Aerospace Science and Technology, Elsevier, 2019. DOI:10.1016/j.ast.2019.02.026
- 6. **Sadagopan, A.**, Camci, C., "Viscous flow and performance issues in a 6:1 supersonic mixed-flow compressor with a tandem diffuser", Aerospace Science and Technology, Elsevier, 2019. DOI:10.1016/j.ast.2019.02.027.

#### Invited talks

- 1. Sadagopan, A., "Fluid-Thermal-Structural Interaction of Cone-Slice-Ramp in High-Speed Flows," Lockheed Martin Advanced Topics in Structural Dynamics Seminar Series, May 8, 2024.
- 2. **Sadagopan, A.**, "Physical mechanism of shear layer oscillation on cone-slice-ramp in hypersonic flows," Penn State Aerospace Seminar Series, Feb 8, 2024.

#### CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

- 1. **Sadagopan, A.**, and Huang, D., "Reduced-Order Modeling for Fluid-Thermal-Structural Interaction of Cone-Slice-Ramp in High-Speed Flows," AIAA SciTech, Orlando, FL 2024.DOI:10.2514/6.2024-1050
- 2. Sadagopan, A., and Huang, D., "Data-driven approach for input-output analysis of quasi-periodic systems," APS Division of Fluid Dynamics, 2023.
- 3. Sadagopan, A., and Huang, D., "Modal analysis of a shear layer in high-supersonic cavity flows using data-driven and operator-based resolvent analysis," APS Division of Fluid Dynamics, 2022.
- 4. Sadagopan, A., Huang, D., Jirasek, A., Seidel, J., Pandey, A., Casper, K., 'An experimental and computational correlation study for fluid-thermal-structural interaction of a control surface in hypersonic flow', AIAA SciTech 2022 Forum. DOI:10.2514/6.2022-0291
- 5. Sadagopan, A., Huang, D., Xu, H., Yang, X., 'Numerical investigation of fluid-thermal-structural interaction for a control surface in hypersonic flow', AIAA SciTech 2021 Forum.DOI:10.2514/6.2021-0911
- Sadagopan, A., Huang, D., Duzel, U., Martin, LE., Hanquist, K., 'Assessment of high-temperature effects on hypersonic aerothermoelastic analysis using multi-fidelity multi-variate surrogates', AIAA SciTech 2021 Forum. DOI:10.2514/6.2021-1610
- 7. Sadagopan, A., Huang, D., Hanquist, K., 'Impact of high-temperature effects on the aerothermoelastic behavior of composite skin panels in hypersonic flow', AIAA SciTech 2020 Forum. DOI:10.2514/6.2020-0937

#### Teaching experience

Teaching Assistant at the Dept. of Aerospace Engineering, The Pennsylvania State University

Duties included grading assignments, designing project questions, conducting office hours, and class recitations.

Courses: Aerodynamics I: Incompressible flow, Aerodynamics Lab and Aerospace analysis (undergraduate level) and Foundation of Fluid Mechanics (graduate level)

#### Coursework Projects

# Large Eddy Simulation (LES) of Incompressible Decaying Isotropic Turbulence

Simulated isotropic decaying turbulence to compare Smagorinsky and Dynamic Smagorinsky models with DNS data in FORTRAN.

# Two-dimensional Transonic Cascade Wind Tunnel Passage Flow Periodicity Study

Validated an axial turbine blade cascade using RANS-based computations in STAR-CCM+. Conducted a tailboard angle variation study to minimize the deviation of  $C_p$  values across the cascade airfoils.

# Professional membership and academic services

American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME)

American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AIAA)

American Physics Society (APS)

Journal reviewer (>1): Aerospace Science and Technology, Journal of Fluids Engineering, Journal of Propulsion and Power, International Journal of Turbomachinery, Propulsion and Power, AIAA SciTech conference, AIAA Journal.

# SKILLS SUMMARY

• Programming: C, Fortran, Bash (Linux), MPI, PETSc, SLEPc

• Packages: STAR-CCM+, ABAQUS, Pointwise, ICEM, ANSYS Fluent, CharLES

• Tools: Matlab, Python (Pytorch, TensorFlow), Mathematica

# Internship

#### Turbomachinery Lab, Bharat Heavy Electricals Limited (BHEL)

Hyderabad, India Summer 2015

Generated a turbine cascade using 'Pritchard' parameters for the given boundary conditions. Estimated pressure coefficient, Mach no. and lift distribution using vortex panel method for comparison against higher-fidelity RANS based computations.

# References

Dr. Daning Huang Assistant Professor Department of Aerospace Engineering The Pennsylvania State University daning@psu.edu Dr. Katya M. Casper Principal Member of Technical Staff Aerosciences Department Sandia National Laboratories kmcaspe@sandia.gov Dr. Cengiz Camci Professor Department of Aerospace Engineering The Pennsylvania State University cxc11@psu.edu